Finding aid to the Elizabeth Heard Bell papers SSC.MS.00256
Sophia Smith Collection
Elizabeth Heard Bell papers
1955-1998
Sophia Smith Collection
Bell, Elizabeth Heard, 1908-1998
SSC.MS.00256
6.667 linear feet (8 containers)
The Elizabeth Heard Bell papers include correspondence, diaries, subject files, clippings, and memorabilia. The subject files include material on many aspects of environmental activism, especially against nuclear energy.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Marcia Grimm in 1994 and 1999.
Biographical Note
Elizabeth Heard Bell (1908-1998) was born and raised in Summit, New Jersey. She lived in Paris for about 5 years in the 1920s, witnessing Lindbergh's landing in 1927. She married (?) Wadsworth, circa 1934, and had 3 children--Dewitt, Marcia, and Linda. They divorced and she married Stanley Bell and had a step-daughter, Ethel. Stanley Bell died in 1984. Both Elizabeth and Stanley were environmentalists associated with Montague Farm, a commune founded in 1968. They knew many local activists and were themselves anti-nuclear activists. She testified for Sam Lovejoy in the 1970s at his trial for destroying a nuclear power tower. In 1982 she published Bittersweet: Poems and Prose.
Scope and Contents
The Elizabeth Heard Bell papers include correspondence, diaries, subject files, clippings, and memorabilia. The subject files include material on many aspects of environmental activism, especially against nuclear energy.
Antinuclear movement--New England--History--Sources; Environmental protection--New England--History--20th century--Sources; Environmentalists--United States--Biography--Sources; Nuclear power plants--Environmental aspects--History--Sources; Political activists--New England--Biography--Sources; Renewable energy sources--United States--History--Sources; Women environmentalists--Biography--Sources; Women political activists--Biography--Sources; Lovejoy, Samuel H.; clippings; Newsletters; Pamphlets; Fliers; correspondence; memorabilia; diaries; Grimm, Marcia; Grimm, Marcia
- 1994 Accession, Accession 1994-S-0026
  - Subject files: Ac-Ea (Box 1)
  - Subject files: Ec-Nuclear (Box 2)
  - Subject files: Nuc-T (Box 3)
  - Subject files: T-W (Box 4)
  - Subject files: Misc. to be filed (Box 5)
- 1994 Accession, Accession 1994-S-0042
  - Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Subject files, 1973-1983 (Box 1)
    - Gill Energy Committee (Box 1)
    - Recycling (Box 1)
    - Gill History Committee (Box 1)
    - Nuclear power (Box 1)
    - Herbicides/Pesticides (Box 1)
    - Samuel H. Lovejoy (Box 1)
    - Alternative Energy Coalition (Box 1)
    - Montague plants (Box 1)
    - Physicians for Social Responsibility: John Gofman and Helen Caldicott (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous clippings and publications (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Paper dolls (photocopies) (Box 2)
- 1999 Accession, Accession 1999-S-0003
  - Elizabeth Bell, yearly Diaries, 1955-1998 (Box 1)